this is what Lego products looked like
in the
1980s and this is a Lego Product
now that's because the company has
become more than just blocks they have
video games movies theme parks all these
activities which ultimately reinforce
the core which is the sale of Lego sets
all that content helped it become the
world's largest toy maker breaking in
billions of dollars every year here's
how the company uses licensing deals in
media to expand it its customer base and
build its content Empire this is the
economics of Lego Lego is 90 years old
it was founded in Denmark in 1932 and
initially it was a company that made
wooden toys but then in the 1950s it
launched its trademark product the one
we all know now the the plastic Lego
brick since then Lego has beat out
Hasbro and metel to become the biggest
toy brand worldwide in the first 6
months of 2022 the company's Revenue h
27 billion Danish croner or about $ 3.47
billion up 177% from 2021 and it's
anticipating growing demand so much so
that the company is building two new
factories in the US and Vietnam Lego has
made the bricks the building blocks of
its business Lego is still essentially a
toy company what what they always say is
their core is still to make the plastic
bricks for kids but of course they do
now do a lot more than that some of
LEGO's first moves into content started
in the 199 90s Island behind us when the
company's sales slumped it was trying
everything from new toys to electronics
to theme parks can you find the power
Bionicle Bionicle came along in the
early 2000s and that was a time when the
LEGO brand was actually in danger of
becoming a little bit stale the bionical
franchise featured buildable action
figures and multiplatform storytelling
agile determined Unstoppable the
franchise built a Content Universe
through Comics books movies and video
games the BET proved successful in 2003
when the toy maker saw a 26% loss in net
sales Bionicle was its bestselling line
and it really revitalized the brand and
and showed them a way that they could
engage audiences with different types of
content with cartoons
movies comics and it wasn't just
Original Stories Lego released its first
sets based off of licensed material in
1999 Star Wars in 2005 it it brought
that into content with a 5-minute short
called revenge of the brick that aired
on Cartoon
Network it was a Twist of course on the
Revenge of the Sith which was the the
Star Wars movie which came out at the
time that really paved the way for the
for the content Partnerships which we've
seen in subsequent years that Lego twist
has since been put to use on all sorts
of franchises like Batman Marvel and
Jurassic world really we're now used to
seeing not just the basic Lego kits but
Lego Star Wars kits and and so on that's
really an integral part of what Lego
does now so it's really the content has
has changed Lego's identity we think of
it as part of these popular franchises
which we all know like Marvel and
licensed material was on full display on
the company's Smash Hit 2014's The Lego
Movie which grossed over $450 million
worldwide it held the top spot in the US
box office for 3 weeks after its release
Superman Wonder Woman the mermaid
Michelangelo and the 2002 NBA allar the
goal of the Lego movie was to Market
Lego to a wider audience I think it was
a lot more successful than anyone
imagined it was a very successful movie
in its own right a big hit at the box
office that laid the template for for a
lot of the content creation that Lego
has done since then Lego and Warner
Brothers released three more feature
films the latest in 2019 none earned as
much as the first of course there is a
risk of oversaturation Lego doesn't want
to do too much but but I think think
they're still very much at the stage of
growing in a lot of markets content has
helped the toy maker break into new
places like China where Lego is growing
its presence of the 66 new stores it
opened in the first half of 2022 46 of
those were in China almost 42% of the
company's 833 locations are there movies
and games assist in raising awareness of
the brand the main challenge Lego faced
in in New Markets like China is that the
grown-ups the parents just don't really
know about Lego they don't have Lego in
their in their own backgrounds like a
lot of grown-ups in in the US and Europe
do and using licensed material in that
content also helps reach more audiences
being part of these popular franchises
like The Avengers for example is a great
way for Lego to to reach out to all
kinds of different Generations people
across the world people who don't
necessarily even know Lego content is
also a way for it to appeal to its adult
fans as the brand has been trying to do
in recent years find your flow
build with Lego bricks reality TV show
Lego Masters for example features adults
building extreme Creations out of the
titular plastic bricks the original Lego
fans took to Lego as kids and they're
now grown up and and a lot of those
people are still very keen on Lego and I
think Lego very smartly realized that a
lot of those people would be willing to
to buy kits that are are pretty complex
pretty expensive and are designed
specifically for for grown-ups the
company has its eyes set Beyond just the
$2 dimensional screen last April Lego
and epic games announced a partnership
to build a digital experience in the
metaverse all of this content certainly
in the company's current thinking the
movies the games that all is there to
support the core product which is the
same as it has been for decades the
plastic brick