this Barnes
& Noble in Pikesville Maryland used to
be in a 24,000 ft space in this building
now it's moved across the street to a
space that's less than half the
size and with the downsizing came a new
look and new books chosen specifically
for this store's customers it's all part
of Barnes & Noble strategy to tailor
each of the company's more than 600
location to local tastes Barnes & Noble
is adopting the strategy of independent
bookstores that it once put out of
business here's how the book seller is
implementing its new approach and why it
thinks this new strategy will sell more
books this is the economics of Barnes
and
[Music]
Noble Barnes & Noble was first founded
in 1873 in 1971 Leonard Rio acquired the
company which set off a period of growth
the retailer went public in 1993 in an
era when it was opening Superstores
across the country in the 1990s and
2000s Barnes & Noble bookstores really
looked like large supermarkets filled
with books usually anchoring strip
centers in the suburbs or rural areas
and whether in Phoenix or Maryland or
Ohio the stores had the same books with
the same furniture and the same layout
it either had one floor or it had two if
had two it had enormous escalators going
out with this huge sort of open space in
the middle to an upper floor that model
happened to be extremely scalable they
were trying to fill their stores with
books and infrastructure at the lowest
cost possible so they wanted to order
all the same types of bookshelves the
same type of furnishings and decorations
and other autra mths so the company grew
and fast those huge stores carried more
books at lower prices than independent
book stores we all remember the romcom
new got mail Joe Fox I'm in the book
business I am in the book business so
many closed when Barnes & Noble came to
town they weren't able to compete with
the title selection or prices that
Barnes Noble offered but big stores and
large inventories weren't enough to save
Barnes & Noble from a digital threat
Amazon was able to offer kind of like
Barnes & Noble had in the past a huge
selection of titles at lower prices than
Barnes & Noble could because it didn't
have the cost of real estate and other
uh costs that Barnes & Noble was
shouldering and it sunk a lot of money
trying to keep Pace particularly in Nook
it's e-reader business take your story
wherever you want it to go but nothing
helped stop the bleeding the company's
Revenue has declined since
2012 then in 2019 hedge fund Elliot
Management Corporation acquired the
chain and installed James da who led
British retailer waterstones and founded
his own independent bookstore da books
as CEO it felt entirely intuitive to me
that you allow each bookstore to run as
an independent bookstore they will
create much more interesting much more
Dynamic much more engaging bookstores
and that meant reminding people about
the appeal of inperson versus online
shopping what you're missing is the
opportunity to kind of read the book
flaps of all the other books that are
there and maybe get recommendations from
the local book seller who's working
there the company says it wanted to
emphasize the experience of visiting a
physical bookstore so its new strategy
strips stores of the cookie cutter look
and feel that had helped the change grow
its revenue and store count some
locations have moved on from The Big Box
model to smaller stores and in these
smaller spaces they are reconfiguring
the stores so that they're more of a
maze and less of a supermarket aisle
plus the company says each individual
store has more autonomy over what books
to order and how to display them here at
the Pikesville Maryland location the
store manager says that customers like
romance books from Black authors and
lots of fiction so the large romance
section is at the front of the store and
there's a huge display right in the
center celebrating Black History Month
store managers can also choose how to
run promotions like this buy one get one
50% off deal on specific fiction books
chosen by the team here Brooklyn has a
very different demographic very
different set of customers a very
different set of book interests to let's
say somebody in Alabama in Georgia who
is the best person to judge what those
particular communities want to by it the
book sellers in those communities the
company has also been listening to its
store managers on wider Trends manga was
a small part of our assortment we had
maybe five six Bays of books on manga
And yet when these book sellers were
reorganizing their stores they were
coming back to us saying we want to do
38 you know we want to do 42 which was
just almost sort of incomprehensible
except that's what they said their
customers would respond to D also used
this localizing strategy to turn around
British books store chain water stones
which reported a 42.9 million pound loss
across 268 stores in 2012 compared to a
16.32 million pound profit across 278
stores 6 years later the two businesses
are on paper identical it had had
identical histories um and had reached
an identical point of failure that's why
Barnes & Noble relinquished some control
to individual stores but that comes with
its own set of of challenges for the
company you could walk into a bookstore
and find out that it's really not doing
well the manager's choices aren't
appealing to customers and books aren't
selling still Barnes & Noble says the
strategy is promising for the first time
in more than a decade the company is
planning on opening more stores than it
closes in
2023 we've seen a balancing in which
much higher percentage of our sales are
coming from books and books are growing
really very dramatically if you run
better bookstores you sell more books