a puma cotton
blend t-shirt on Vince's site cost $85
but the same shirt sells for $29.99 at
TJ Maxx so why does it cost less over 10
years the off-price retailer has opened
263 more stores in 2022 TJX which owns
TJ Maxx Marshalls and Homegoods brought
in almost $50 billion in sales revenue
more than Nordstrom's and Macy's
combined and the secret to its success
the company isn't shifting most of its
business online or using big data to
figure out what Shoppers want instead
it's sticking to a decades old Playbook
get the max for
minimim
[Music]
it's this is the economics of TJ Maxx
there are really two components to TJ
Maxx's strategy the bargain and the hunt
One Way TJ Maxx gets discounted Goods is
by buying excess merchandise and cancel
orders from other brands and retailers
essentially it takes advantage of
surplus and waste in the retail system
this allows the company to sell its
merchandise generally around 20 to 60%
below regular retail prices but there's
a catch just the fact that the price is
low is not enough what you need is also
a reference price because people don't
know how much things cost that's where
Alex says something known as the
anchoring effect comes in at TJ Maxx
most items have two prices the T J Maxx
price and a comparison price people
anchor the the regular price and then
they see exactly how much of a deal
they're getting and this way they really
understand what the value is that DJ
Maxx provides to them take these Rag and
Bone shorts a TJ Maxx in Manhattan sold
them for about $40 with a comparison
price of $50 that's a 20% discount but
the original price tag happened to be on
these shorts and it lists the price as
$195 that would be around 80% discount
and that comparison price is really just
an estimate on TJ Maxx's website there's
a message next to the comparison price
that says these prices are references to
regular retail prices where identical
items are not available we compare to
products of a similar type quality and
style these price tags aren't the only
way TJ Max helps customers feel like
they're getting a bargain the whole
positioning of of TJ Maxx is U if we
give you brand names for Less
and the reason why it's important is
because very often when you see low
price uh you think it's low price
because the quality of the product is
low but if the customer knows and trusts
the brand then they won't assume the
price is low because it's a bad product
instead Alex says they'll attribute it
to TJ Maxx's ability to get discounted
goods and because people often expect
name brand items to be more expensive
the brand itself acts as an anchor
emphasizing the fact that as a customer
you're getting a
deal uh makes people feel good it's not
only I'm getting a low price but I'm
actually getting a deal uh which makes
people feel good about themselves that
they're smart Shoppers TJ Maxx says it
gets its goods from about 21,000 vendors
and the inventory in its stores is
constantly turning so as a result people
tend to go more often to this type of
stores and also spend a little bit more
time in the store in search of something
across its companies TJX employs more
than 1200 buyers that each control
millions of dollars and has authority to
cut deals on the spot as a buyer for TJ
Maxx I'm always on the hunt let's say
you have a bathing suit brand and it's
the right before Memorial Day weekend
and they're stuck with extra bathing
suits that's when TJ Maxx buyers show up
at the showroom you know they can cut a
deal right on the spot and they can get
it to their stores within a week
department stores on the other hand can
take weeks to review and approve orders
from their buyers so TJ MOX buys the
merchandise quickly and gets it into the
store just as fast they have a saying
internally door to floor in 24 meaning
that any merchandise that shows up at a
store in the morning has to be on the
sales floor by the end of that day to
ensure speed merchandise often arrives
at stores already on racks that
employees wheel off trucks and move
straight onto the sales floor and once
it's there all the merchandise is laid
out differently than other retailers too
helping to create that treasure hunt
experience while most department stores
group items by brand TJ Maxx organizes
its inventory by type this means that
different brands can end up next to each
other on the same racks and since TJ
Maxx doesn't have walls dividing
sections of the stores or Brands it can
easily reconfigure the layout based on
changing inventory seeing all the
products and changing layout can
encourage impulse buying Shoppers know
that if they see something they like
they need to buy it now if they wait it
may be sold out or hard to find when
they come back once you take it home
things are changing dramatically because
now you're not buying something you you
are giving up something lots of research
has shown that giving up something is
more difficult than acquiring you're
willing to uh pay more uh not to give up
something than to buy something
retailers struggled through the rise of
e-commerce in the pandemic and while TJ
X's off-price retailers still took a hit
they have bounced back in 2021 TJX had
the highest sales in the company's
history a record it then beat the
following year and it's not because TJ
Maxx and the other off-price retailers
adapted but rather because they never
drifted away from their core strategy TJ
Maxx tends to perform pretty well in an
economic downturn because that's when
customers tend to be bargain conscious
and you know they offer really good
value for the money