this is what
Nintendo originally was yes it was a
playing card company and this is
Nintendo today me Mario consoles theme
parks even movies so what has driven the
$44 billion Empire this is the economics
of
Nintendo Nintendo is different from its
competitors Sony and Microsoft thanks in
part to its lowcost Hardware Microsoft's
Xbox makes no profit on its Hardware
consoles are actually sold at a loss in
the market so when somebody goes and
they buy an Xbox at their local retailer
uh we're subsidizing that purchase
somewhere between $1 and $200 with the
expectation that we will recoup that
investment over time through accessory
sales and storefront and Sony only
recently began to make a profit on the
PlayStation 5 then there's Nintendo
their technology is usually five or six
years behind in terms of
state-of-the-art but that means that
they're cheaper to produce and that
means Nintendo is much much more
profitable on their Hardware business
about half of Nintendo's profit in 2022
came from Hardware Sales they've
dominated the market when it comes to
handheld consoles one of its big
successes the Game Boy launched in
1989 Nintendo was really early to the
party uh with handheld they're kind of
credited with inventing the console
although they were probably third or
fourth the game boy had a longer battery
life compared to some of its competitors
for four Shades of Gray nuanced gameplay
and had Tetris one of the top selling
video games of all time eventually
Nintendo's Game Boy became the third
most sold console in the company's
history selling 119 million units to
date the company continued to innovate
releasing new hardware for its games
from the GameCube Nintendo DS the wiii
and to its most recent success the
switch with more than 122 million units
sold you can play it at home like a
console on your big screen TV but you
could pick it up and take it on the go
and it becomes a handheld device and
that's pretty novel we haven't really
seen anything that's a hybrid like that
before sales of the switch device and
its games accounted for about 94% of
Nintendo sales revenue in its 2021
fiscal year and today it's the second
bestselling game console in Nintendo's
history and continues to be a driving
factor of its Revenue the success of
Nintendo's consoles is also due to its
software in other words its games in
2022 Nintendo had had 19 first party
titles that sold over a million units
each exclusive to its consoles the
difference between the others and
Nintendo is that Nintendo historically
has produced about 50% of all the games
sold on its Hardware system and the
other guys are typically under 10% of
the game sold on their systems so they
make a small fraction of the software
that's played on PlayStation and Xbox
Nintendo makes more than half recent
Point Animal Crossing New Horizon's
release in April 2020 created higher
demand for the only console carrying it
the switch Nintendo makes games
exclusively for the most part for its
own devices if you want to play a
Nintendo game like Legend of Zelda you
need Nintendo Hardware in fact
Nintendo's first party games generate
over 70% of its sales its best sellers
in 2022 were all Nintendo first party
games and the type of content Nintendo
makes is also different than its
competitors let's keep in mind
Nintendo's characters are very
cute
Mario Nintendo is known for making
familyfriendly games for the most part
so it appeals to a different crowd than
some of the other Publishers you won't
see blood or Gore or foul language but
even Nintendo couple years ago dabbled
into the shooter genre when we think of
Shooters right we think of Call of Duty
fortnite uh they take a very
familyfriendly approach with Splatoon
it's a shooter but you're shooting
paintballs the company's next iteration
bringing these familyfriendly characters
to a larger Arena and building another
generation of fans in February 2023
Nintendo opened its first theme park
outside of Japan and in April it's
releasing a Super Mario Brothers movie
starring Chris Pratt it's a me a Mario
that's smart because that's going to
expose the Nintendo brand to hundreds of
millions of people who haven't ever
owned a switch I don't think that
Nintendo is necessarily worried about
whether somebody who goes to the theme
park will buy buy a Nintendo console or
buy a game but they want those people to
be aware of the Nintendo Brands and they
want them to know who Mario is and who
Zelda is and who Yoshi is and who Pikman
is it is risky to start a new franchise
and sometimes new properties just don't
resonate um but they have plenty a very
deep library and they've stuck with that
for the most part and iterated on it and
modernized it we'll probably be playing
Legends of Zelda for another 20 30 years
Mario is probably not going anywhere you
now he's just going to live forever and
keep that mustache and keep everyone
happy for many years to come