let's say you wanted
to buy a popular Rolex Daytona watch a
new one would cost you
$14,800 but if you wanted to buy a used
version of the same watch you might need
to pay over
$38,000 so why people spending more
money to get a used Rolex if you use
your watch primarily for 10 in the time
then we're not of the same mindset
here's why the used watch Market is
booming and what Rolex is doing to get
in on the action this is the economics
of used
[Music]
Rolexes experts suggest that it takes
about a year to make a Rolex and weight
list for new watches can last months to
years and because of that these days you
can't walk into any Rolex store any
Rolex dealer and just get any watch that
you want for the past few years as
demand has increased Rolex has not been
able to keep up with that demand their
production just can't match the number
of people that want a Rolex if you've
got 10 $220,000 to burn you really want
a watch you're probably going to go to
the resale Market because the watch that
you want is going to be available there
and so the prices on the resale Market
have then gone up because there's more
people going to that market 29% of
collectors reported paying more than
retail price for their most recent
pre-owned watch according to a report
from Boston Consulting Group and 40%
said that one of their top reasons was
that they were able to avoid long
waiting lists in the firsthand Market
this has created a boom in the secondary
Market pre-owned watch sales reached 22
billion in 2021 the used sector is
actually growing faster than the primary
market and for some people used watches
are worth more than new ones that's
because some rare styles are more
desirable or because Rolex has
discontinued certain models and colors
in in older model Rolex can have a
patina it can have some wear marks and
so those kind of personal details those
kind of personal age marks those are
things that collectors might want there
is also a bragging rights thing where if
you have a Rolex from the 70s or the 80s
you're able to say it's from this era
it's you know 20 30 years older than I
am and that is just kind of cool to
collectors in a way the market about a
decade ago was softer than it is right
now back then you could sell a watch and
get a return on it but you could also
sell a Rolex and it could have
depreciated value when you could lose
money on it these days you now will
likely make more money off of it if you
sell it on the resale Market much of the
success of the used watch Market is due
to the rise of online watch resale
marketplaces over the past decade that's
where people like Paul and Carol come in
can yell at get over there buddy the
husband and wife Duo run Bob's watches
an online Marketplace for buying selling
and trading luxury watches they say that
they currently have one of the largest
selections of used Rolex watches in the
world I started out in the watch
business because I could see that there
was no real safe transparent honest
place for people to buy and sell
pre-owned watches it's been an upward
Trend since 2010 we've been growing
consistently about 30 to 40%
year-over-year two years ago we did uh
$100 million in sales there's so much
more for us to tap into that we haven't
had the bandwidth to get to because the
growth has been so so fast and furious
and Paul and Carol love Rolexes sales of
used watches online already exceed
auction and store sales and one report
predicts they're going to reach close to
60% of the secondhand luxury Market by
2026 during the pandemic the stock
market goes crazy you have the kind of
crypto phenomenon you have meme stocks
happening and people have a lot of extra
capital and they're taking that in many
cases and they're putting it toward
assets um luxury goods and in a lot of
cases watches starting in 2020 used
luxury watches sold for 1.5 to three
times their retail prices Rolex is a
brand that's really recognizable in its
design it's you know easy to spot on the
street and a lot of people they'll see
that their friend has a given Rolex and
they think I want that too but Rolex the
company only sold new watches which
meant that the brand wasn't involved
with used watch sales that is until late
2022 Rolex opened a certified pre-owned
program for its used watches retailers
can send used Rolexes that are at least
3 years old back to the watch maker the
certified pre-own program verifies that
a watch is an authentic Rolex and works
properly then retailers can sell the
watch with an official Rolex certificate
the program is already active in one
retail chain in six different countries
another chain of official Rolex
retailers in the US will enter the
program this may buying a watch with
Rolex certification could be a draw for
firsttime buyers you're buying a watch
on the internet it can be a little bit
of a daunting experience of all the
watches on our website today almost 50%
of them already have the original box
and papers from Rolex we've offered a
CPO program a certified pre-owned
program now for almost 5 years the only
thing really new about it is that Rolex
is certifying and doing the paperwork
behind it so I don't feel that there's
any increased competition but I do feel
that the market is big enough for
everybody to participate today people
buy Rolexes online the way that they
might buy toilet paper so it's really
not a premium or specialized experience
there's still that consumer that wants
to have that experience of going into a
store of being waited on of kind of
being shown watches from a glass display
case and making it feel more special
because they're buying something of such
a high value this certified pre-owned
program means that Rolex can take a cut
out of a market that it previously left
untapped but things might continue to
shift for the luxury watch Market the
used watch Market is cooling down as
sellers eager to make a profit have
flooded the market with inventory recent
data shows the number of Rolex watches
available to buy second in hand roughly
doubled from the beginning of 2022 to
September of the same year on those
really coveted kind of brand name
watches so to speak the ones that
collectors talk about the resale value
has gone down a little bit resellers
people that watch that market they do
say that the prices have come back down
to earth a little bit but the volume of
sales the amount of sales happening that
Still Remains pretty high we're seeing
still a large number of transactions in
the resale Market your day and day out
Rolex is still retaining a lot of value
on the resale Market you can still get a
pretty good return turn for it as with
any resale Market there is a risk that
the Rolex Market can fall out at any
time 5 years ago we might not have been
talking about how crazy this Market is
and 5 years from now we might not be
the market is so large that to a certain
extent both things can be true you know
people that watch this Market will say
that that's just actually a reflection
of how big the market is now where it
can behave in many different ways just
because it is this kind of really large
transactional Marketplace