your last pizza probably
came in a box like this it's cardboard
stur and most importantly keeps your
cheese from getting stuck to the lid and
that's thanks to Domino's whose founder
is widely credited with creating the
corrugated pizza box it's just one of
the company's Innovations not in pizza
but in
delivery in 2022 more than 40% of online
delivery orders for major pizza chains
were from dominoes here's how the
company made its name in the pizza
delivery market and why this
foundational piece of its business is
facing new challenges this is the
economics of
Domino's Domino's it's a
Del dominoes originally called Dominics
acquired its first restaurant in 1960 in
ipsilanti Michigan and jumped into the
delivery business the same year
something very few restaurants were
doing at the time you're now we think of
delivery as being so ubiquitous I mean
so many types of restaurants have
delivery But Domino's was there very
early at scale one reason it's become so
well known for its delivery is a
campaign the company started in the 80s
PR ing delivery in less than 30 minutes
within 30 minutes only Domino's Pizza
delivers in 30 minutes or less people
really did have the sense that once they
ordered that pizza they were going to
get it to their homes quickly and I
think that really helped for marketing
Domino's ended that guarantee in 1993
after a delivery driver struck another
vehicle resulting in a lawsuit but by
then the company had cemented its place
in delivery and in the half century
since Domino's was founded it's paid off
it took the biggest slice of pizza chain
sales in
2022 Domino's success is due in part to
creativity and every step of its
delivery process starting with stores
many are small and often with little or
no dining space a model the company has
said allowed for lower rents and reduced
store expenses over the years Domino's
has also focused on establishing more
than 6,500 locations in the US and has
worked with franchisees to extend their
reach
so one part of Domino's strategy is
what's called Fortress which is making
sure there's enough pizza shops in a
certain mile radius that wherever your
order goes one of those pizza shops can
handle it and it can help get it to your
house quickly the company's supply line
is also structured to make the pizza
creation process as quick and uniform as
possible Domino's has 25 supply chain
centers in the US where dough is mixed
and toppings are prepared before being
sold to to franchise stores where pizzas
are assembled and baked the more pizzas
that are sold the more money Domino's
makes from its supply chain it made up
59% of Domino's Revenue in
2021 the next part of the process is
ordering in 2008 the company rolled out
its Advanced online ordering system
which included a customized Pizza
Builder and the Pizza Tracker so the
Pizza Tracker is something that Domino's
invented they will let you know where it
is in the process it's whether it's
being cooked whether it's out for
delivery where they're approaching
Domino's has continued to introduce new
ordering options Pizza Emoji sent
Domino's ordered smiley face then
there's the last step of the process
getting the pizza from the kitchen to
your home from working with special
kinds of insulated bags to creating 3D
car top signs Domino's has been a big
innovator in this step the company has
experimented with several methods of
delivery vehicles helicopters electric
bikes self-driving cars even cars with a
heated Pizza Oven it's really putting
the whole brand behind delivery in a lot
of ways but after years at the top of
delivery Domino's is facing new
challenges companies like Uber Eats
GrubHub and door Dash are eating at
Domino's business in the US as drivers
leave pizza for apps with more flexible
hours it's contributed to an
industrywide delivery driver shortage
other chains like Papa John's and Pizza
Hut have both started working with some
of these apps but Domino's has resisted
they argue that that makes it more
profitable because you're not having to
pay an outside service to deliver that
pizza and to Market that pizza on their
app and it keeps them closer to their
customers as the company has faced these
issues its shares have slumped from a
high at the end of
2021 now Domino's is exploring new
options the company is building out a
fleet of electric delivery vehicles to
recruit new drivers ERS and it's now
offering customers what it calls a $3
tip to pick up their own pie we see you
carry out Heroes you know it's much
cheaper for them if their customers pick
up their own pizza and so they are
getting in the pickup game in a big way
as Domino's continues to Grapple with
these issues investors and customers
will be watching for future
[Music]
Innovations