businesses find all sorts of ways to
stand apart from their competition from
cutting out the middleman to bucking the
e-commerce trend  We explore the
strategies behind some of the biggest
names in business to see what makes them
profitable unique and able to survive or
even thrive in an economic downturn
first we dive into how Trader Joe's
threatened conventional supermarkets
with its limited options and cult
favorite products  these are bananas
obviously they're from Trader Joe's
today they cost 19 cents each and about
25 years ago bananas at Trader Joe's
cost 19  as of 2020 Trader Joe's gross
average sales per square foot was more
than double those of other major grocery
store chains and it's been ranked the
highest rated grocery store for customer
satisfaction  so how does Trader Joe's
manage to keep prices low while out-
competing traditional grocery stores by
selling fewer
products  this is the economics of Trader
Joe's  Trader Joe stores are smaller and
they tend to carry fewer items and the
vast majority of what they sell is
private label  when the store first
opened in 1967 Trader Joe's founder Joe
Coulombe emphasized stocking products that
were unconventional to Shoppers at the
time like Dijon mustard and granola in
1979  Trader Joe's was bought by the
German discount grocery store chain Aldi
Nord  and today Trader Joe's has built
its image around selling trendy quirky
and seasonal items orange chicken K
pasta sauce from Trader Joe's  it helps
with fueling the experience for
customers people can go and kind of feel
like they're discovering something new
and these products have created a large
and loyal customer fan base  I went to
Trader Joe's and I accidentally got I
got way too much stuff  of course I love
Trader Joe's  it's popularity on social
media is helpful for the company because
Trader Joe's doesn't do a lot of
advertising  actually the grocery store
doesn't do a lot of things that other
grocery stores do  there's no loyalty
program no online shopping platform and
no Deli counter  still the Trader Joe's
fan base is strong and they are
dedicated they are Mega fans   people will
sell Trader Joe's products on places
like eBay for a much higher price tag
than what you would find at the stores
Trader Joe's smaller selection can make
the in-store shopping experience more
efficient for customers according to
psychologist and Professor Barry Schwarz
for example instead of having to pick
between many different brands of tomato
sauce at a conventional grocery store
customers at Trader Joe's can quickly
select one from its more limited options
by selling a small selection of house
Brands  Trader Joe's can control its own
supply chain which it says brings down
prices   Trader Joe's items tend to be
cheaper because they buy directly from
producers and manufacturers whenever
they can so this cuts costs that would
typically go to the middleman and the
company says they are able to pass that
along to Shoppers   Trader Joe's says it
buys in bulk and often pays for items up
front whenever possible from suppliers
this all helps lower prices the grocery
store chain also says it pays for some
products like Dijon mustard in local
currency so if the currency fluctuates
Trader Joe's takes on the risk not the
supplier and by assuming the risk Trader
Joe's says it can negotiate better
prices with suppliers  this control over
its products and supply chain means
Trader Joe's can easily add and remove
items from its shelves
one of the unique things about Trader
Joe's is they're constantly changing
their shelves if products aren't selling
as well as they thought they would  they
remove them from their shelves to make
room for something better  some grocery
stores charge Brands various marketing
fees to stock products but Trader Joe's
says it only makes money when customers
make a purchase  so according to Trader
Joe's this incentivizes it to only stock
product that customers like from JoJo's
sandwich cookies to kungpow chicken
there isn't really another chain that
does what they do  there are other
Discounters that sell for cheaper but
you're not going to find the Innovation
and and the fun products there  the
traditional grocery stores have tried to
go that route but Trader Joe's is Trader
Joe's