spaces Chipotle's menu only has a few
items but it's highly customizable born
in 1993 that's what's made Chipotle one
of the most successful fast casual
restaurant chains in the US but in
recent years Chipotle's faced many
challenges between 2015 to 2018 Chipotle
dealt with five foodborn illness
outbreaks like most of the restaurant
industry Chipotle's Revenue took a big
hit during the beginning of the coron
virus pandemic and today it's dealing
with inflation that's increased labor
transportation and food costs yet
despite these setbacks Chipotle sales
are actually growing here's how
Chipotle's focus on efficiency and
Innovation helped it bounce back and
become one of the country's most
valuable Quick Service chains this is
the economics of
Chipotle Chipotle's Revenue has
increased by more than 200% over the
past decade its stock price has
increased about 400% in The Last 5 Years
much of Chipotle's success comes from
its efficient and what it calls
transparent instore experience Chipotle
has really in a lot of ways made the
whole fast casual category for
restaurants it's not fast food it's not
full service they've generated a lot of
sales from people who want this
alternative that's seems fresher and
faster than fast food but it's not a
full service experience fast casual
design can help them reduce some of
their labor expenses which helps with
profits Chipotle's menu is relatively
small but it's easy to customize there's
tons of stuff you can put on your meal
that's proteins that's cheeses that's
vegetables that's all the salsas and
sauces and for customer that makes it
exciting you know they get lots of
different things they can customize
their meal with the more limited menu in
general is better for restaurants and
their profits it's less things to train
the restaurant workers on it's less
waste Chipotle's founder Steve ell
emphasized having an open kitchen he
wanted customers to be able to see the
ingredients and preparation in front of
them today employees work at individual
stations to serve already prepared
ingredients making the ordering process
more efficient for customers we can
serve as many as 100 customers within a
15-minute period what's a better way
than telling people that it's fresh
showing them let them come in and
discover for themselves this
transparency has been very important for
Chipotle especially after its food
safety issues after several outbreaks of
eoli salmonella and norovirus in
Chipotle restaurants the company
implemented several changes like
improving food preparation and storage
procedures encouraging sick employees to
stay at home and bringing on a new CEO
Brian nickel he really did emphasize
that they cleaned up their procedures
didn't happen immediately but with time
people start to forget things too there
hasn't been the big high-profile scares
that there were previously after several
outbreaks between 2015 and 2018
Chipotle's stock price took a hit
however its focus on its digital
ordering platforms helped Drive drive up
revenue and stock prices started to
climb back in 2008 Chipotle became one
of the first fast casual chains to
create an online store pickup model in
its first year Chipotle's digital sales
accounted for $13 million or just 1% of
its total sales in 2022 digital sales
grew to $3.4 billion that's now nearly
40% of Chipotle's food and beverage
Revenue if you're ordering online
digitally that is made for you at a
whole separate part of the kitchen which
is just dedicated to online orders
Chipotle's app and online ordering
systems were also vital during the
pandemic the pandemic obviously was
terrible for all restaurants but
Chipotle did have some advantages there
in that they had this whole digital
ordering platform really set up and
scaled beforehand when the pandemic
first hit we saw that people stopped
going to restaurants for some period of
time so we saw our sales drop uh pretty
significantly but it only took like a
week or two before we started to see
that while they first stopped visiting
restaurants the adoption of the digital
ordering really picked up very very
quickly and so I would say within the
first four weeks we had our digital uh
uh ordering soore from about 18% to it
at one point hit 70% Chipotle also
designed its stores to have two separate
prep stations called make lines one make
line is just for inore orders and the
other is for digital and Catering orders
this made food pickups quicker for
customers who didn't want to spend time
indoors this idea that we had the
digital make line so that as people were
ordering we could make food on the
digital make line and also serve
customers that were choosing to come in
so it was a seamless experience like
most stocks during 2020 they were still
lower than they were before the pandemic
but by the end of the first year into
the second year most stocks had you know
fully recovered we had our all-time high
in 2021 recently Chipotle has continued
to expand its digital ordering services
with a new pickup option for customers
called chipot Lanes let's go ahead and
take offer all the convenience of the
drivethru but when you order ahead of
time you know exactly what time to come
and so there's no ly you drive up and
you pull to our window you get your food
and off you go the first chipot Lane
opened in 2018 and there are already
nearly 600 across the US Chipotle says
at least 80% of new restaurant locations
opening in 20123 will have chipot Lanes
but that's just one example of how
Chipotle has continued to innovate to
attract customers social media has been
great for us because in addition to
making sure we're serving you know the
meals that that customers come to expect
at Chipotle we also want to be part of
culture Chipotle frequently uses social
media to attract younger consumers by
releasing recipe videos animated short
films Roblox games and social media
campaigns like the lid flip challenge
with major influencers Chipotle has also
used social media to drum up excitement
about new menu items and innovate its
menu options to keep up with consumer
Trends adding new things for customers
is very important to Chipotle and they
have a whole process for this where they
try and try these items in house really
test and learn before they test in
stores they like menu news whether it's
you know a steak item or a chicken item
alpastor quesadillas they want to keep
customers interested even if most of
their menu is staying the same so what's
next for Chipotle in general the online
ordering even when you pick it up in the
restaurant is just much more efficient
the company says it wants to open more
locations that are only used for online
pickup orders they won't have any
seating for customers this will also cut
down on labor costs since workers won't
need to clean seating areas and
bathrooms as often we think the idea is
let the customers choose which channel
they want now our job is to make sure
every channel is convenient it's easy
it's fast so that we don't give any
friction whatsoever but make sure every
experience that you can provide on every
channel is a great one