Joe's  let's say you wanted to buy this
Primark t-shirt if you're shopping on
primark's website you'll quick discover
that you
can't over the past 10 years e-commerce
sales have more than doubled but last
year European fast fashion retailer
Primark made 9.5 billion in sales
revenue without a single penny from
online shopping we made a very clear
choice and our Clear Choice is bricks
and mortar this comes at an uncertain
time for struggling clothing retailers
retailers like Forever 21 JC Penney and
Neiman Marcus have closed stores and
filed for bankruptcy and while a UBS
report shows up to 880,000 retail stores
will close in the next 5 years Primark
plans to expand to 60 stores in the same
time frame is driving 2 hours from
Toronto to Buffalo to shop at Primark
worth it heck yes I used to fly 6 hours
to do so so how is primar expanding
without online shopping this is the
economics of Primark fashion retailer is
is incredibly competitive more so than
ever there's not many players especially
in fast fashion that are making
fat margins pretty much the thinking
everywhere is that you have to have this
online presence but online shopping is
actually incredibly expensive for
retailers you have to have a logistical
hub from which you would dispatch the
goods and then You' probably have a
local distribution center from which you
have to do last mile delivery each step
of that just is an extra layer of cost
that just eats away at the margin which
in fashion is very very slim anyway but
the real killer for e-commerce is that
somebody who buys something on the
Internet is far more likely to return
that product than somebody who goes into
a store returns are one of the biggest
profit losses for online retailers on
average processing a return for $100
worth of merchandise bought online costs
a company $ 2650 for years online
retailers just ate these expenses only
now are more of them deciding to pass
the cost back to the consumer Primark
have just said right from the beginning
we don't think we can make money out of
e-commerce we're not even going to going
to try we're going to focus all our
resources on the physical store and
protect our margins and that wasn't an
issue for the retailer until now Primark
is expected to close all 189 of its UK
stores tonight and it doesn't have an
online offering to fall back on
e-commerce was a Lifeline for a lot of
retailers during the pandemic they
couldn't open their stores but they were
still able to make some sales on the
internet but Primark didn't budge even
as consumers urged for it to offer
online shopping and even after its
Revenue dropped by almost 22 billion and
I think their confidence in this model
of having no digital sales and only
using stores I think was probably shaken
by the pandemic who knows what would
have happened if it had gone on for
longer I think the closures weren't
quite long enough to really tip the
scales and force them to fundamentally
rethink the model instead of traditional
online shopping in 2022 Primark launched
a trial service called click and collect
in select UK stores customers can select
certain products online then pick up
their orders in store so Primark still
has some cost to maintain its website
but it's cheaper than running a true
online shop so Primark makes a sale but
they don't have any of the logistical
costs that would be involved in packing
it up and then shipping it out to your
home and there's another bonus for
Primark since the customer has to go
inside to collect their purchase they're
likely to browse around and maybe even
buy more they make the sale online but
then they have a good chance of making
some extra sales when that person visits
them consumer psychologists call this
shopping momentum essentially once
you've already decided to make a
purchase it's easier to justify adding
more to your cart it always feels just
overwhelmingly busy with people who are
in there looking for bargains and it's
not just clothing Primark lures
consumers with beauty home and travel
products similar to a department store
what we like to say about primar here in
the US is that you know we're all
treasure without the hunt so customers
may go in for a new t-shirt and leave
with a suitcase but a Primark that I can
drive to and don't have to fly to is a
dream because that means there's no
limit to what I can buy and bring home
to carry this vast selection of items
Primark finds large retail spaces
because it relies on selling a lot it's
one of the largest retailers in the UK
by volume and one of the largest across
all of Europe last year Primark made
about 9.5 billion in sales revenue in
part by selling a lot of things at low
profit margins and it does this by
sourcing a lot of its clothing from Asia
combined with not offering online
shopping this enables primar to sell its
merchandise at lower prices even lower
than many other fast fashioned retailers
where they do have serious rivals on
Price is with the digital only players
like shien for example they are often
even cheaper than Primark but according
to the National Retail Federation 80% of
shopping still happens in store giving
Primark an edge over its digital only
competitors even so its instore shopping
model got off to a rocky start in the US
Primark opened its first Us store in
Boston back in 2015 although it was
already popular in the UK its us
expansion started slowly over 4 years it
opened nine stores after years of
experimentation primar learned it would
have to change to succeed in the us when
we first opened we took a similar store
size that we would have had in Europe
but when Primark opened its stores
across the Northeast it struggled to
find the right store density what they
found in the US is that retail is so
much more competitive there's a lot more
retail in
downtown areas in the US and than there
is in the UK for example so you just
can't support a massive store it's just
not possible to get enough revenue for
the size to support its large stor sizes
it needed a lot of foot traffic but
unlike the UK stores which were located
in constantly busy areas Us stores were
mostly in malls where during the week
foot traffic dwindled we learned that
actually 35,000 ft of retail selling
space is is actually the The Sweet Spot
for us they didn't face the commercial
pressure that a a publicly owned company
might have faced to suddenly open a 100
stores and and get really big ready
quickly and then possibly risk disaster
because they hadn't thought it through
the culture of primarch has always been
to take our time and and to test and
learn and we've done that in every
country where we've introduced the brand
this wasn't about you know growing
market share at all costs and the
overall retail Market is Shifting online
shopping hit a peak during Co but now
growth is beginning to slow as people
return to stores and I think that's
never been so important as it is since
we came out of Co I think there has been
a massive rediscovery of being in malls
being together physical shopping and I
think as a business that took the
decision a long time ago to to have that
as our core strategy um you know has
continued to allow us to be
successful